<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anthrōpasthenez, a good ground to cease from confidence in man discovered in a sermon upon Isaiah 2, verse 22 / preached at Clement Danes, the last day of the sixth moneth, 1651, by George Masterson.</title>
            <author>Masterson, Geo. (George)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27554495</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27554495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50108)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1728:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anthrōpasthenez, a good ground to cease from confidence in man discovered in a sermon upon Isaiah 2, verse 22 / preached at Clement Danes, the last day of the sixth moneth, 1651, by George Masterson.</title>
                  <author>Masterson, Geo. (George)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Husband,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title printed in Greek letters.</note>
                  <note>Running title: A good ground to cease from confidence in man.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah II, 22 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>A GOOD GROUND To ceaſe from Confidence in Man: Diſcovered in a SERMON upon <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2. verſe 22. Preached at <hi>Clement Danes,</hi> the laſt day of the Sixth Moneth, 1651. By <hi>George Maſterſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nobis Albada non niſi Albada eſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Lipſ. adverſ. Dialogiſtam.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Ut nihil habet eximium, ita veniâ certè indigna non eſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Hu: Grot: Ben: Aub: Maurerio Epiſt.</hi> 43.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Man is like to vanity, his days are as a ſhadow that paſſeth away. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 144.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Now behold thou truſteſt upon the Staff of this bruiſed Reed, even upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> on which if a man lean, it will go into his hand and pierce it. So is <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> unto all that truſt on him. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Kings 18.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Husband.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110136:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110136:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the truly Honorable JOHN BRADSHAVV Lord Preſident of the Councel of State.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe was preached in faith, and it is in humility caſt at your Lordſhips feet. It was judg'd by ſome (in the day that it firſt ſaw the light) <hi>like Apples of Gold in pictures of Silver.</hi> The complexion of your Affairs is (through the admirable goodneſs of God) far different from what it was in the day that my Soul travailed with theſe Meditations. A golden Vial of Contempt (from the hand of the Lord) is poured out upon the heads of your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: and the glorious Succeſs that the Lord hath crowned your Army with, may ſeem to render the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Exhortation <hi>(Ceaſe from man)</hi> unſeaſonable, Tet (my Lord) if it be judged uſeleſs to every other purpoſe, it may ſerve as a Teſtimony of my Fidelity and Affection to the Commonwealths Cauſe.<note place="margin">Grotius B: Aub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maurerio Epiſt, 25.</note> 
               <hi>Dulce eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum fidem ex auxiliis cognoſcere, etiam cum jam eorum uſum ſpe celerior victoria intercepit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:110136:3"/>But I am bold to hope (the Bleſsing of the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying of it) the publication will not be in vain even at this day; For I have heard by the hearing of the ear (and experience it but too much in mine own breaſt) that the deſire of glory is ſcarcely laid aſide (even by good men) till they put off their mortality: <hi>Cupido gloriae etiam ſapientibus noviſſima exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itur, Strada</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> proloc. Acad. <hi>2.</hi> It is eaſier to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Armies abroad, then ſubdue Luſt at home. <hi>Adeo excellentibus ingeniis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livius de Fabio.</note> 
               <hi>citius defuerit ars ut ſeipſos regant, quam ut hoſtem ſuperent.</hi> Though the publique Enemy have been made as ſtubble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Sword, yet there are darts in the hand of Satan, which if they be not quenched by an opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Faith, will ſtrike through the Liver of the State. The dart of Pride glorying in your own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel or ſtrength, is a deadly dart: If you attribute any thing to man,<note place="margin">Haeret lateri lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalis arundo. Virg.</note> you will deſtroy in one moment the glorious Fabrick which the Lord hath been ſo long in building, and cemented with ſo much precious Blood.</p>
            <p>It is obſerved of <hi>Timotheus</hi> the Athenian, who having done many great Services for the State in his Government, and giving an Accompt thereof to the People (according to their cuſtom) concluding every particular with this Clauſe, <hi>And in this For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had no part:</hi> that he never proſpered in any thing he took in hand afterward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> The face of the enſuing Diſcourſe is ſet againſt the Wiſdom and Strength of man, as they are (falſly) judged a foundation of Confidence, and if your Lordſhip caſt an eye upon it, you will
<pb facs="tcp:110136:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>there finde the Lords end in the terrible Work that he hath wrought for you in Righteouſneſs, viz. <hi>That the Lord alone might be exalted in that day.</hi> The <hi>Man of the Lords right hand, the Choſen man</hi> will prove but a lye if he be leaned on. I deſire to render the honor that is due to the precious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the Lord hath made uſe of for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of this great Work from the beginning: and mine eye runs down in ſecret becauſe of the wormwood and gall, the bitterneſs of ſome mens ſpirits againſt them; Yet I dare not ſay of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument (no, nor of all) as <hi>Florus</hi> of <hi>Marius, Actum eſſet de Repub: niſi illi ſeculo</hi> Marius <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingiſſet,</hi> The Commonwealth had been deſtroyed, had not he or they been raiſed up. The Speaker, the General, your Lordſhip, with the reſt that are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Lord in Parliament and Army, are po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Shafts: but the hand that made you ſuch, can do as much for, and by a Stake out of the hedge.</p>
            <p>When the Lord had prepared a Gourd to be a ſhadow over <hi>Jonah's</hi> head, the Text ſaith, <hi>So</hi> Jonah <hi>was exceeding glad of the Gourd:</hi> and immediately it follows, <hi>But God prepared a Worm when the morning aroſe, and it ſmote the Gourd that it withered,</hi> Jonah <hi>4.6, 7.</hi> Your Army is a Choice Gourd, it hath been hitherto (under God) a Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow from the heat: Confidence in them will breed the Worm, and cauſe them to wither when the Sun ariſeth. But I forget my ſelf too much in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsing upon your Lordſhips precious time,</p>
            <q>
               <l>In publica commoda peccem</l>
               <l>Si longo Sermone morer tua tempora.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horat.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt</hi> 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:110136:4"/>That the Lord who hath called you to an high Place, would keep your heart in a frame of exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that he who hath made you eminently faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Commonwealth, in the great Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof, would inſtruct you to be faithful to your own Soul in the Concernments of Eternity, is, and ſhall be the continued prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The meaneſt of thoſe that honor your Lordſhip for vertues ſake,</hi> Geo: Maſterſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110136:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 2.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Ceaſe ye from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E meet the Prophet (in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter) having his feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of Peace, his lips dropping with an Evangelical Prophecy, which divides it ſelf into two ſtreams (flowing with Milk and Honey) In the firſt, we have the glorious future Eſtate of the Church: <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In Noviſſimis diebus, tempore ſcil. Meſſie Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch. Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitur ultimam aetatem mundi, ſcil: tempus ab adventu Meſſiae in carnem, uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad diem judicil. Eſtius. Hunc lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ſublimiore ſenſu de Meſſiae temporibus, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Hebraei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligunt, Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</note> 
               <hi>laſt days, that the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mons domus Domini, i e. ipſa domus Domini, Eſtius. Mons dom: Dom: i.e. Eccleſia, Menoch</note> 
               <hi>mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the top of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the hills; and all Nations ſhall flow unto it, and many people ſhall go and ſay, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3. This glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious eſtate of the Church is illuſtrated here by three things. 1. Its Exaltation; <hi>The mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be exalted above the hills:</hi> 2. Its Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; It ſhall be<note n="c" place="margin">Fundatus, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus, ſtabilitus, hoc enim ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat Hebraeum nachon Menoch.</note> 
               <hi>eſtabliſhed in the top of the mountains.</hi> 3. By the Confluence to it; and<note n="d" place="margin">Omnes, ſcil: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omni natione aliqui. Eman: Sa:</note> 
               <hi>all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall flow unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond, we have her Peace as a River, and her Proſperity as a mighty Stream, illuſtrated by the wonderful effects of it at the fourth verſe, <hi>They ſhall beat their ſwords into plow-ſhares, and their ſpears into pruning-hooks: nation ſhall not lift up ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110136:5"/>nation, neither ſhall they learn War any more;</hi> and more fully (where this Prophecy is again repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Micah, cap. 4. ver. 4. <hi>But they ſhall ſit every man under his vine, and under his fig-tree, and none ſhall make them afraid.</hi> A man would expect now, that this halcion Prophecy ſhould be brought forth in a ſweet calm, that there ſhould not be a frown upon the face of (that great Ocean) the world, when it is brood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and hatch'd by the Spirit of God: But behold, the ſhaking of the Earth terribly, the removing of Mountains, levelling them with the duſt, uſhers in the eſtabliſhment of the Lords Mountain; ſharp pangs and bitter throes precede this Birth; deſolation and deſtruction, the alarm of War, the voyce of the Trumpet, neighings of Horſes, claſhings of Armor, rollings of Garments in blood go before this bleſſed Peace, ver. 11 and 12. <hi>The lofty looks of man ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſs of man ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day: for the day of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low:</hi> and again ver. 19. <hi>They ſhall go into the holes of the rocks, and into the caves of the earth, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his majeſty, when he ariſeth to ſhake terribly the earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 55.9.</note> and in the end of the 21 verſe: Thus Gods ways are higher then our ways, he brings light out of the womb of darkneſs, eſtabliſhment out of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; the deſire of all Nations, by the ſhaking of all Nations:<note place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note> Now the Lord walking in ſuch an inſolent way, the Prophet beſpeaks the Church <hi>ver.</hi> 5. to have her eyes upon God: <hi>O houſe of Jacob, come ye and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110136:5"/>let us walk in the light of the Lord:</hi> they that walk not in this light, grope after God (in many of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations) as a blinde man; they that walk not in this light, ſtumble and fall under every cloud, which God, in the wiſdom of his providence, brings upon the houſe of <hi>Jacob;</hi> their ſoul is caſt down, and their ſpirit diſquieted in them whenever the Enemy is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, though he be lifted up but to be thrown down with the greater violence: On the other hand, they that walk in this light, know, that <hi>when the wicked ſpring as the graſs, and when all the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity do flouriſh, it is, that they ſhall be deſtroyed for ever,</hi> Pſal. 92.7. They that walk in this light, know that when the day of the Lord is upon the proud and lofty, upon the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and upon the Oaks of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> upon the Ships of <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the high Towers; it is that the Lord alone ſhould be exalted in that day: Now when the Lord ariſeth to do this, he will do it by his own arm, <hi>his arm ſhall rule for him;</hi> therefore he beſpeaks the Church, <hi>Ceaſe from man,</hi> &amp; he will do it againſt all oppoſition; whatſoever, therefore he adviſeth Enemies, <hi>Ceaſe from man.</hi> The Romiſh expoſitors do generally interpret it of Chriſt, the man Chriſt Jeſus is the man (ſay they) here ſpoken of; and to ceaſe from him, is in their ſenſe,<note n="e" place="margin">Serio vos moneo ut quieſcatis a vexando, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> occidendo Chriſto, qui homo quidem eſt, ſed etiam Deus ſcelerum vindex, Menoc: in loc. Significatur magnanima ira indignatio &amp; vindicta, quam in ſuos hoſtes Chriſtus exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, Idem.</note> 
               <hi>To take heed and beware of offending or killing Chriſt, who although he be man, yet he is God alſo, and by the breath of his noſtrils, the fierceneſs of his anger will avenge himſelf upon his enemies.</hi> But the Prophets ſcope in the whole Chapter, ſtands in oppoſition to ſuch an Interpretation; the meaning therefore is,<note n="f" place="margin">Nolite Fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam in ullo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ponere, Grot. Annotat.</note> 
               <hi>Place not your confidence in any of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110136:6"/>ſons of men,</hi> as <hi>Grot.</hi> or (as the learned Divines in their Annotations) <hi>Seeing all humane helps and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſtays will fail, and no might or height will be able to ſecure any when God comes to execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: be admoniſhed and adviſed to caſt off your vain Confidence in frail and mortal man.</hi> The words then are a Dehortation anſwering <hi>(ex adverſo)</hi> that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. and they hold forth<note n="g" place="margin">Deo adhaere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcite, &amp; ab ipſo toti pendete, non ab hominibus. Jun, in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Dependence upon God, in ceaſing from man.</hi> We may obſerve in them:</p>
            <p>Firſt, A <hi>Tacit</hi> Suppoſition, <hi>viz. Man is exceeding prone to place his Confidence in man.</hi> Secondly, An expreſs Dehortation, <hi>Ceaſe from man.</hi> Thirdly, The Enforcement of this upon a double accompt, or two Arguments to ſtrengthen the Dehortation. The firſt general, in the end of the verſe: <hi>There is nothing in man to be accounted of,</hi> therefore ceaſe from him. The ſecond more particular, <hi>His breath is in his noſtrils,</hi> therefore ceaſe from him. One word of the Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiiton, Man is prone to confide in man: By Man in the Text we underſtand any thing that is not God, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is very frequent in the ſcripture, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation here anſwers the Exhortation in the fifth verſe, To walk in the light of the Lord. All means, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, ſecond cauſes, are Man: Strength is man, and Policy is man, &amp; Riches are man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon theſe the ſons of men are prone to lean, prone to cleave to them, exceeding forward to ſit down under them, to confide in them. The eyes of carnal men are ſet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (in a direct line) upon man. Godly men have too frequently a caſt with their eyes, they look (oblique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) too much upon means. <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> coming up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110136:6"/>
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with a great hoſt, makes fleſh his arm, placeth his Confidence in man, 2 <hi>Kings cap.</hi> 18. from the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the end of the 35<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Goliah</hi> had his eye fixed upon man, when he diſdained <hi>David,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>a youth and ruddy, and of a fair countenance,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.42. and forward. <hi>Babylon</hi> alſo leaned upon man when ſhe ſaid, <hi>I ſhall be a Lady for ever;</hi> when ſhe ſaid in her heart, <hi>I am, and none elſe beſides me, I ſhall not ſit as a widow, neither ſhall I know the loſs of children,</hi> Iſaiah 47.7, 8. And as wicked men look wholly upon man, ſo the Saints on earth have not their eyes wholly taken off from man. <hi>David</hi> looked ſinfully upon man, when he commanded <hi>Joab</hi> to go through all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from <hi>Dan</hi> even to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> and to number the people, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.2. and he may be apprehended to glance at man in the ſixth verſe of the thirtieth Pſalm, <hi>In my proſperity I ſaid, I ſhall never be removed.</hi> The ground of this is, becauſe Saints are ſometimes led by ſenſe, carnal men are wholly ſenſual, therefore is their hope anſwerable to their preſent viſible help: if there be more with them then againſt them, they become confident of ſucceſs: if they march with Twenty thouſand againſt him that comes forth but with Ten thouſand, they are ready to make their boaſt of Victory;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.11.</note> But becauſe <hi>the Race is not to the Swift, nor the Battel to the Strong,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſaith the Spirit) <hi>Ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils: for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Churches Duty (and it will be the wiſdom of her Enemies) in the day that the Lord ariſeth to ſhake the earth,<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> to ceaſe from man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:110136:7"/>
               <hi>O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>truſt thou in the Lord: he is their help and their ſhield. O houſe of</hi> Aaron <hi>truſt in the Lord: he is their help and their ſhield. Ye that fear the Lord, truſt in the Lord: he is their help and their ſhield,</hi> Pſa. 115.9, 10, 11. <hi>It is better to truſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in man: It is better to truſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in Princes,</hi> Pſal. 118.8, 9. <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſon of man, in whom there is no help,</hi> Pſal. 146.3. It will appear to be the Churches Duty to ceaſe from man upon a three-fold Account.</p>
            <p>The firſt Reaſon is founded upon the Relation in which the Church ſtands to God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 1.</note> All her relations oblige her to ceaſe from man, and to put her confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God: To inſtance but in two; as he is her Lord, as her Husband.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as her Lord: <hi>If I be a Maſter, where is my fear?</hi> Mal. 1.6. Confidence in God is an eſpecial part of that fear (the ſervice) which he requires at the hands of thoſe that make profeſſion of him as their Lord and Maſter: Now unleſs we ceaſe from man, we can never give God that fear which he challengeth. The Lord Chriſt tells us, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24.) <hi>No man can ſerve two maſters: for either he will hate the one and love the other, or elſe he will hold to the one, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the other.</hi> He that holds to God deſpiſeth man: He that cleaves to man deſpiſeth God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As her Husband: God hath married the Church unto himſelf; every Believer is eſpouſed to God by the Miniſtration of the Goſpel, <hi>I have eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you to one husband,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.2. 'Tis the firſt and great part of the wives conjugal duty, to ceaſe from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110136:7"/>all other men. The Law of Marriage runs thus, <hi>A man ſhall leave his Father and Mother, and cleave unto his wife: and they ſhall be one fleſh,</hi> Geneſ. 2.24. As therefore a wife deals treacherouſly when ſhe departs from her husband, and cleaves to another man, ſo are the Lords people ſaid to deal very treacherouſly with him, when they put their confidence in any thing but him, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 3.20. compared with verſe 23. At the twentieth, <hi>As a wife treacherouſly departeth from her husband, ſo have you dealt treacherouſly with me, O houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaith the Lord.</hi> Wherein her departure from God conſiſted, is made manifeſt by her return at the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, <hi>Behold, we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord our God:</hi> And how come they? In an humble Acknowledgement of their folly in cleaving to the Hills, confiding in the multitude of Mountains. <hi>Truly in vain is Salvation hoped for from the Hills and from the multitude of Mountains: truly in the Lord our God is the Salvation of</hi> Iſrael. That's the firſt Account upon which it appears to be the Churches Duty to ceaſe from man, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe of the relation ſhe ſtands in to God.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Accompt is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 2.</note> (that which is generally laid down by the Prophet) becauſe there is nothing in man to be accounted of; nothing in man that you may rationally account a Ground of Confidence. There are two things in man that paſs for a ſure foundation upon which others may build their Confidence in man, his Wiſdom, his Strength: his Wiſdom to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent dangers and inconveniences: his Strength to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them. Thus <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> to <hi>Hezekiah, Thou ſayeſt I have Councel and Strength for the War,</hi> 2 Kings 18.20.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110136:8"/>But I ſhall endeavor to render both theſe, ſandy foundations, upon which the houſe that is built will not ſtand.</p>
            <p>The wiſdom of man (firſt) is not a ſufficient foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for us to build our Confidence on him. The Spirit of God tells us, <hi>That vain man would be wiſe,</hi> Job 11.12.<note place="margin">Caryl. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>It is not his vanity that he would be wiſe, but that he would be thought wiſe, that he affects the reputation of wiſdom more then the reality of it.</hi> There is a natural itch in man to be thought wiſe, even fools would be judged wiſe, and the wiſeſt reputed wiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the line of what they have attained to: And as it is natural with man earneſtly to deſire this; ſo he cannot want thoſe who will be exceeding prone to impute it to him, very ready to ſet this Crown upon his head. If a man be able to ſee any thing at a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſtance, or in a clearer light then vulgar and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon eyes do, he apprehends himſelf, and is judged by others to ſee beyond the Moon. <hi>Irrefragable, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refutable, invincible Doctor,</hi> are but modeſt Epithetes, <hi>Angelical</hi> and <hi>Seraphical</hi> are affected by, and vainly attributed to ſome men. One ſays of <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Cujus nomen non tam homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quam ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae nomen eſt. Strada prolus. Acad. l prol. 4.</note> 
               <hi>That the Name which expreſſeth him, might but ſerve to ſet forth wiſdom:</hi> And the ſame Author of <hi>Jerom, That</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eo praeconio exornatus eſt, ut diceretur, Ab nullo hominum ſciri, quod Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymus ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Idem l. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the induſtry of a man could not attain the knowledge of that which he was ignorant of.</hi> And the Lord <hi>Montaigne</hi> hath exalted <hi>Turnebus</hi> above the rate of Mortality, when he leaves him under this character, <hi>A man who knew all things.</hi> But the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſpeaks of mans wiſdom in a lower key, <hi>Job</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Vain man would be wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caryl. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>though man be born like a wilde aſſes colt. The beſt have ſomewhat
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110136:8"/>of the beaſt in them. Every man is brutiſh by his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Jeremy 51.17. and we experience it daily, that it is with the greateſt wits as with<note n="k" place="margin">Statium inter Poetas magnas virtutes magnis vitiis adaequaſſe. Strada l. 2. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Acad. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Statius</hi> among the Poets, or <hi>Alexander</hi> among the Heroes, they miſs as oft as his, and the number of their follies are at leaſt anſwerable to their rational productions, and this comes to paſs becauſe ſtrength of parts is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſtrong temptations, &amp; luſts are not weakned or ſubdued wholly by the power of Nature: hence<note n="l" place="margin">Bacons Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Learning 2. B. p. 303. quart.</note> 
               <hi>though the logical part of ſome mens mindes be very good, yet the mathematical part is very erroneous: they judge well of conſequences, but not of proportion and compariſon, preferring things of ſhew and ſenſe, before things of ſubſtance and effect.</hi> But notwithſtanding this (which were there no more, is enough to enforce the Argument, and withdraw Confidence from man upon the account of his wiſdom) let it be ſuppoſed that a man (or company of men) is as wiſe as he (or they) pretend to, or (which is much more) are judged by others to be: Suppoſe him to have as clear a light and as ſharp an eye as a ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> is capable of: his luſts ſubdued ſo far, that all his concluſions do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the dictates of his Reaſon, without turning aſide to his luſts in any of them; yet is not ſuch wiſdom in man to be leaned upon,</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe he hath not a ſpring of wiſdom in himſelf, but it is conveyed to him by a ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit-pipe from God. The man upon whoſe Counſel I can confidently build, ought to have a ſpring of wiſdom in himſelf, leſt (though his counſel be as the Oracle of God to day) I conſulting with him in my ſtreights (to morrow) finde him dry, not able to give
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110136:9"/>a right anſwer, becauſe the Pipe is cut off. It is with man in all his ſufficiency as with <hi>Bezaliel</hi> and <hi>Aholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi> whoſe wiſdom and underſtanding by which they wrought for the ſervice of the Sanctuary, was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts by the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 36.1. Since then the Spring of mans wiſdom is in Heaven, and it is in the hand of the Lord to cauſe the ſtreams to flow, or binde them up at his pleaſure, or to turn it into folly, (as in <hi>Ahitophel</hi>) or to mix a perverſe ſpirit with it, (as in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Counſellors, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 19.13, 14.) <hi>The Princes of</hi> Zoan <hi>are become fools, the Princes of</hi> Noph <hi>are deceived, they have alſo ſeduced</hi> Egypt, <hi>even they that are the ſtay of the Tribes thereof: The Lord hath mingled a perverſe ſpirit in the midſt thereof.</hi>) Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man is not to be confided in, or the lips of any of the ſons of men to be cleaved to in reſpect of his wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Again ſecondly, The wiſdom of man is no ground of Confidence, (ſuppoſe him as richly furniſhed as he is capable) becauſe God is wiſer then he: though a man be wiſe to lay his Deſign in the womb of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wiſe to project the critical minute of bringing it forth, yet is he not to be confided in, becauſe God is wiſer to fruſtrate his Deſign, to make it as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely fruit of a woman. <hi>When the Kings of the earth ſet themſelves (and the Rulers take counſel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed, then he that ſits in the Heavens laughs, the Lord hath them in deriſion,</hi> Pſal. 2.2. &amp; 4. Thus the wiſdom of man appears a ſandy foundation of Confidence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſtrength of man is no more a rock then his wiſdom was. The natural property of man
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110136:9"/>is weakneſs, ſtrength is but accidental to him: thus <hi>Sampſon</hi> tells <hi>Delilah</hi> (enquiring wherein his great ſtrength lay, <hi>Judges</hi> 16.7.) if they binde me with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven green withs that were never dried, then ſhall I be <hi>weak, and be as another man.</hi> A man is naturally for ſtrength (not as a Lion or Horſe, but) as a worm, <hi>Job</hi> 25.6. <hi>How much leſs man, that is a worm, and the ſon of man who is a worm?</hi> It were ſingular vanity to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a worm as a pillar of Marble, no leſs folly to look upon the ſtrength of man as a brazen wall. But let us give man ſtrength, let his neck be clothed with thunder, let his ſtrength be the ſtrength of ſtones, his bones as braſs, and his ſinews iron; Let his Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates be many and potent, the Troops of his valiant ones exceeding numerous, his Reſerves as great moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains at the heels of one another, let the Towers of his defenced Cities reach unto Heaven, yet is he not a foundation of Confidence in reſpect of his ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe his ſtrength is but permiſſive, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Man is not ſtrong according to the pleaſure of his own will, but after the good will and pleaſure of God: So that when man ſaith, <hi>I will purſue, I will overtake, I will divide the ſpoil: My luſt ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied upon them: I will draw my ſword, my hand ſhall deſtroy them,</hi> it many times comes to paſs that in the greatnes of his excellency the Lord overthrows them: <hi>The Sea covers them, they ſink as lead in the mighty waters,</hi> Exod. 15.9, 10. The ſtrength of man may be (as <hi>Jeroboams</hi> arm) <hi>withered when he ſtretcheth it out furtheſt.</hi> Therefore his ſtrength is no ground of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
            <p>Again, becauſe his ſtrength is limited. God hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110136:10"/>ſet bounds to it, and thoſe bounds are unknown to us, therefore we are not to confide in the ſtrength of man. A man in his ſtrength may ſwell as a mighty ſtream, he may rage and roar like the Sea, but (as to it, ſo) to his ſtrength God hath ſet bounds, and ſaid, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou go, and no further.</hi> If the Lord lift up a ſtandard againſt any man (though he come rolling in as an overflowing flood) he ſhall become weak as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Now we being ignorant of the bounds that God hath ſet to the ſtrength of any, are not therefore to confide in any ſtrength of man: The Lord may have appointed <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Hic murus ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneus eſto. Hor. Epiſt. l. 1. Ep. 1.</note> 
               <hi>brazen wall to their ſtrength,</hi> a pillar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond which they cannot paſs in that occaſion, or at that time, in which we expect their arm to be ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out as of old.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We are not to hang upon the arm of man, becauſe the ſtrength of God is infinitely greater then mans ſtrength. <hi>If I ſpeak of ſtrength, lo, he is ſtrong, Job</hi> 9.19. We (treading in the ſteps of this expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) when we would extol a man in the perfections of any quality, uſe to ſpeak at the ſame rate, <hi>What do ye ſpeak of knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caryl. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>why there's a learned man! What do ye talk of riches, why there's a rich man indeed!</hi> So emphatical is the Expreſſion here, <hi>If I ſpeak of ſtrength, lo, he is ſtrong:</hi> Infinitely ſtrong, above the line, beyond the proportion of all others. God is ſo ſtrong, that <hi>though</hi> Babylon <hi>ſhould mount up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and though ſhe ſhould fortifie the height of her ſtrength, yet from me ſhall ſpoilers come unto her, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 51.53. The Lord is ſo ſtrong, that he can weaken the ſtrength of any: <hi>He poureth contempt upon Princes, and weakneth the ſtrength of the mighty,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110136:10"/>Job 12.21. Or ſecondly, cauſe weak inſtruments to tread down ſtrength, <hi>O my ſoul,</hi> (they are the words of <hi>Deborah,</hi> Judges 5.21.) <hi>thou haſt troden down ſtrength:</hi> Or laſtly, turn their Canon upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, cauſe them to fall upon their own ſword, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them by their own ſtrength. <hi>I will overthrow the Throne of Kingdoms, and I will deſtroy the ſtrength of the Kingdoms of the Heathen, and I will overthrow their chariots and thoſe that ride in them, and the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and their Riders ſhall come down every one by the ſword of his brother,</hi> Hag. 2.22. Thus you have a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Account, upon which it appears to be the Churches Duty to ceaſe from man.</p>
            <p>Man is not to be confided in,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe his breath is in his noſtrils.</hi> They that by Man (in the Text) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Man Chriſt, muſt by the breath in his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, underſtand alſo ſomething to render him (not deſpicable, but) terrible.<note n="n" place="margin">Magnanima ira, indignatio &amp; vindicta, quam in ſuos hoſtes Chriſtus exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. Menochius in loc. So Origen. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym. Alvarez. and moſt of the Popiſh Writers.</note> 
               <hi>By the breath in his noſtrils is meant</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>the magnanimous anger, the fierce indignation of Chriſt, with which he ſhall blow upon his Enemies in the day of vengance;</hi> but as we do not entertain their ſenſe of man, ſo we ſhut the door againſt ſuch an interpretation of the breath of his noſtrils; and following our late learned Divines who render it, Whoſe life is ſo frail, that if his noſtrils be but ſtopt that he cannot breath freely, he dyes, whoſe life as a puff of winde paſſing through his noſtrils, may be very ſoon and ſuddenly gone. So alſo the learned <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, whoſe</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Cujus ſpiritus &amp;c Vita ejus ab aere pendet, quo intercluſo peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Grot. in loc. Sec Job. 27.3.</note> 
               <hi>life depends of air, which failing he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to his duſt.</hi> We uſe it as an Argument to dehort from Confidence in Man, whoſe breath is in his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils: Were the wiſdom or ſtrength of man (in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110136:11"/>a foundation of Confidence (which yet they have appeared not to be) this were enough to deſtroy that foundation, <hi>His breath is in his noſtrils,</hi> he is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to diſeaſes and infirmities: When you expect the man to go forth with your Forces, a fit of the Gout or Stone hath rendred him unſerviceable: There are a thouſand Infirmities incident to mans body; Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians reckon two hundred diſeaſes belonging to the eye, his beſt ſtate is (not a ſtate of certainty, but) of danger,<note n="p" place="margin">Ipſam quoque <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo vacare me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici negant. Grot, Epiſt. 81. B. Maurerio.</note> 
               <hi>Verily every man at his beſt ſtate is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vanity,</hi> Pſal. 39.5. Yet (take him with all his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities) could he live ever, there were ſome ground upon which the foot of a mans Confidence might ſtand; but <hi>his breath is in his noſtrils,</hi> and thus he ſtands in ſlippery places that confides in an hourly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying creature. <hi>Tumor momento enaſcens, momento evaneſcens;</hi> we laugh at the folly of our little ones when we ſee them rejoyce in, or grieve for (ſigns they ſet their hearts upon them) the bubbles that are born and die in a moment.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of God is very copious in deſcribing the brevity of mans life, <hi>Is there not an appointed time to man upon earth? are not his days alſo like the days of an hireling?</hi> Job 7.1. <hi>Man that is born of a woman is of few days, and full of trouble,</hi> 14.1. <hi>Man dieth and waſteth away: yea man gives up the ghoſt, and where is he?</hi> 10. <hi>As for man, his days are as graſs,</hi> Pſ. 103.15. He is called <hi>Corruptible man,</hi> Rom. 1.23. And as his breath is in his noſtrils, ſo there are many ways of ſtopping it, various means of depriving him of it: heat, cold, drought, moiſture, a prick of a pin, a ſtone of a grape, an hair, any thing, nothing: Some have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110136:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>died ſneezing, yawning, weeping, laughing:<note n="q" place="margin">Mille viae le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi, Strad. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cur Steruuentesſalut. Unus introitus, innumeri exitus.</note> 
               <hi>Zeuxes</hi> died laughing at the picture of an old woman, which he drew with his own hand. <hi>Sophocles</hi> was choked with the ſtone in a grape: <hi>Diodorus</hi> the Logician died for ſhame that he could not anſwer a joculary queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on propounded at the Table by <hi>Stilpo. Joannes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſius</hi> preaching upon the raiſing of the woman of <hi>Naim</hi>'s ſon from the dead, within three hours after died himſelf; 'Tis folly then to put our confidence in him, of whom (if he be but a days journey from us) we cannot be confident that he is alive. Thus you have the firſt Branch of the Doctrine made good, It is the Churches duty. And <hi>it will be the wiſdom of the Churches Enemies to ceaſe from man:</hi> The Spirit of God tells you, <hi>there is no king ſaved by the multitude of an hoſt: A mighty man is not delivered by much ſtrength; an Horſe is a vain thing for ſafety, neither ſhall he deliver any by his great ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 33.16, 17. and the ſame Spirit dehorts you from confiding in the ſons of the Mighty: <hi>Put not your truſt in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor in the ſon of man in whom there is no help,</hi> Pſal. 146.3. You have doted upon the name of a King, you have idolized Kings,<note place="margin">The Book of Sports.</note> you have prefer'd them to God himſelf: when God hath commanded one thing, and your King another,<note n="r" place="margin">Si aliud Deus, aliud Imperator ju beat, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pto hoc, obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perandum eſt D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Auguſt;</note> contemning the Commandment of God, you have yielded obedience to man; and therefore the Lord hath poured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon them, brought them down from the Throne into the duſt. The name of King is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in victory by the Parliament of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: It is become a name that will devour the man and his fathers houſe, that (openly) makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110136:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of it in this Land; Ceaſe therefore from man: Had the Churches Enemies a Spring of Wiſdom in themſelves, or were they wiſer then God, then you might rationally ſay a Confederacy to them that ſay a Confederacy; had the Enemy an Independent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited, infinite ſtrength; were his arm ſtronger then the Arm of the Lord, then you might ſecurely cleave to him, own him, confide in him; but ſince their Counſels have been infatuated, their Power is limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Lord hath them (as he hath the Devil) in a Chain; Ceaſe from man: <hi>Depart I pray you from the Tents of theſe wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, leaſt ye be conſumed in all their ſins,</hi> Numb. 16.26. The Lord hath begun to break the arm of their Power,<note place="margin">The Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> routed.</note> and he hath ſet it upon the hearts of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to believe that he is at hand, to accompliſh his work in righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Having thus endeavored to make good the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the Improvement of it will be directed to the Church in a double Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the practice of the Duty, to Ceaſe indeed from Man: Truly the Lord is worthy to be wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in our eyes in two things; reſtraining the growing Power of the Enemy, and cauſing the Horn of his Servants to flouriſh. For the firſt, the Enemy did (and might very rationally) expect that if he could ſet the ſole of his foot (his wearied foot) upon Engliſh ground, his ſtrength would take root downward, and bring forth fruit upward; it could not but be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on all hands, that the further he roll'd the greater ſtrength he would gather; that before he had paſſed through one Countrey, he would become a mighty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110136:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mountain; yet behold (and admire God) though at his entrance he leave our Army Fourſcore Miles in his Rear, their fleſh wearied, and their ſpirit almoſt languiſhing through the continued difficulties they met with in a ſtrange Land; though he appear in a County very fond of him, that invited him in, where the Deſign was laid, he coming in according to the cue that he had from hence, though he ſtrike many<note n="f" place="margin">Facile ignem concipiunt quae paulo ante ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctae ſunt faces, Strad: de Bello Belgic.</note> ſparks among Brands lately quenched, that are but too prone to take fire; and though he march with an Idol in the head of his Army, <hi>The name of a King,</hi> to which the generality of this Nation are very ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, too ready to bow down to it, and ſubmit their necks to a Tyrants feet (four Circumſtances, that were each of them big with the ruine of all that is dear to us) yet behold (I ſay) the Cords of his Tent (through the goodneſs of God) are not ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, his Horn is not exalted, there are no (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable) Cubits added to his Stature, his Strength is at a ſtand, much about the ſame ſcantling it was when he fled out of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for our Armies, though they were ſcattered here and there, not onely in the corners of our own, but the moſt conſiderable part of them in a Forraign Land; the Lord hath gathered them together with his Arm, united them in a Body, made them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with the increaſe of God, and given them to overtake the Enemy: I beſeech you therefore, ſince the Lord hath done this for us, made us ſtrong, and not ſuffered the ſtrength of the Enemy to increaſe, do not you ſpoil the Friends of their ſtrength, or clothe the Arm of your Enemy with might, by placing your confidence in man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:110136:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>O think you hear the Army of your Friends (that have been wont to Conquer, who ſcarce know how to flye before an Enemy) ſpeaking in your ears to this effect: <hi>We are going up this day, in the Name of the Lord, againſt a Potent, Numerous, Skilful, Revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Bloody Enemy; were thier Power, Number, Skill doubled, were their Rage and Fury ſeven times hotter, yet would we not be diſmaid, we would not ſtop our ears againſt the Lords call, nor withhold our hands from his work;</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ego nihil mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi tribuo, ſed nee valde mihi metuo a tali Antagoniſta, Lips: adver: Dialogiſt.</note> 
               <hi>we are not in the leaſt afraid of Enemies, but we are afraid of you our Friends; fear hath taken hold upon our hearts, leſt you ſhould fight againſt us by putting your confidence in us; leſt by looking upon us as your preſent help in trouble, you ſhould provoke the Lord to withdraw his preſence from us: we are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, notwithſtanding all our unworthineſs, and your vain confidence, this precious Cauſe of the Lord ſhall proſper: but our Lives may be Sacrificed upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your folly, and the Lord may chaſtiſe your fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confidence, by breaking the arm of fleſh in pieces, if you do not ceaſe from us (for what are we to be accounted of, and is not our breath in our noſtrils?) the Lord may refuſe to go up with us, and then we ſhall be weak, even as a company of other men; we ſhall turn our backs in the day of Battel, yea, we ſhall flie when no man purſueth: we beſeech you therefore, by all our Watchings and Faſtings, by all the hunger and cold that we have undergone for you, by all our Blood that hath been ſpilt as water, by the Scars of all thoſe wounds which we have received for you; Ceaſe from man: By all your Enjoyments, by all your Relations, Wives, Parents, little Ones; by your Liberties Temporal, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110136:13"/>Ceaſe from man: As you love Zion, as you value the Goſpel, as you prize your Priviledges, as the glory of the Lord is dear to you; Ceaſe from man: we are not worthy to ſay, for our ſakes, but for</hi> Sions <hi>ſake, and for the Goſpels ſake, yea for your Souls ſake, and for the Lords ſake we beſeech you, Ceaſe from man:</hi> And I beſeech you hear them in that which they ask at your hands, ſince all that is dear to you is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it. And that I may faſten this duty upon your hearts, I ſhall make uſe of three Conſiderations as Nails.</p>
            <p>Conſider firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſider.</hi> 1.</note> That the end for which the Lord ſhakes the Earth, why he humbles the lofty ones, and bows down the haughtineſs of man, is, That the Lord alone may be exalted: <hi>The lofty looks of man ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſs of man ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day,</hi> Iſaiah 2.11. and again, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. Now when we place our confidence in any thing but God, we exalt it into the Throne of God; the Lord may and doth delight to uſe Inſtruments (not out of neceſſity, but in a way of good will) he may and doth put much honor upon thoſe he makes uſe of, as the Hinges upon which a State turns; but he will never endure that the honor which is due unto his Name ſhould be given to any Inſtruments whatſoever. The Brazen Serpent, when the People burn Incenſe to it, muſt (though ſet up by the eſpecial appointment of God) be broken in pieces: Golden Inſtruments in the Lords hand, are rendred <hi>Nehuſhtan</hi> (a piece of braſs) by putting our confidence in them. We might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to this day (thoſe <hi>dear Names</hi>) <hi>White,</hi> and <hi>Pym,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110136:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Hamden,</hi> and <hi>Brooks,</hi> and <hi>Rainsborough,</hi> and <hi>Thornaugh,</hi> and <hi>Ewres,</hi> and <hi>Graves,</hi> &amp;c. had not our confidence in them been a Dart through their Live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>;<note n="u" place="margin">Magiſter eſt hodiernus, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternus Error: Bel. Belg. Homines poſt damna pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores ſunt, ac docent plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quae nocent. Idem.</note> be wiſer for the future, and that you may enjoy your Worthies, Ceaſe from them.</p>
            <p>We ſhould Proclaim our ſelves unworthy of ſuch Inſtruments, did we not thankfully acknowledge to the Lord, his ſingular goodneſs, in <hi>raiſing up ſeven Shepherds, and eight Principal Men for us in</hi> the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Councel of State, in filling their hearts with Courage and Zeal, to take the Lyon by the Beard, to execute Juſtice upon the head of the great Offender: we have great cauſe to acknowledge to the Lord their faithfulneſs, when we have<note n="w" place="margin">Mont. Eſſays.</note> beheld <hi>many ſurvive their own Reputation, ſeeing (with their own eyes) the honor and glory buryed which they had formerly purchaſed:</hi> yet the Lord hath not raiſed them up that they ſhould exalt themſelves, or be lifted up into the room of God by us, but that they ſhould be an higher Scaffold for the building up of his glory.</p>
            <p>Your hearts cannot but rejoyce before, and to the Lord, in behalf of the General; that the Lord (out of the eſpecial reſpect he had to his People) created him, and raiſed him up for us <hi>(and we remember the time too)</hi> furniſhed him with ſuch rare Endowments for that high Employment, that he who would take a compleat General, muſt limb after his Copy: We can ſay, <hi>That the Horſe and his Rider have been broken by him, the Captains and Rulers broken in pieces:</hi> We can ſay, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Sola Ducis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma interdum Bella profliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, Str: Bel. Belg.</note> Name of <hi>Cromwel</hi> hath been a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to the Enemy; but this onely, as he hath been <hi>a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110136:14"/>Battel-ax, and weapons of War in the hand of the Lord,</hi> for the Exaltation of the Name of the Lord, not that we ſhould exalt him above the Line of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in the Lords hand.</p>
            <p>Did we not make our boaſt of God in our Army, we ſhould ſin: Did we not acknowledge that <hi>he hath taught their hands to War, and their fingers to fight,</hi> Did we not bleſs the Lord for them, that <hi>offered themſelves ſo willingly to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> that in the abſence of dear relations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo chearfully in the midſt of ſo many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, It would be an evil in us not to boaſt (in God) of their unparallel'd Valor, matchleſs Unanimity, and unwearied Labors; yea (as <hi>Strada</hi> of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and Duke of <hi>Alba</hi>)<note n="y" place="margin">Orangius pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam oderat Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Albanum, &amp; clam admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur, Strad: Bel: Belg:</note> the hearts of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies admired them in ſecret for theſe things, though openly their mouths overflow'd with their reproaches; yet the Lord hath done all this, that himſelf alone might be exalted.</p>
            <p>The Enemy is not ſo<note n="z" place="margin">Nihil tam fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum cui non ſit periculum ab invalido. Idem.</note> inconſiderable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſider.</hi> 2.</note> as to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed upon any carnal ground whatſoever. It is true, (upon a ſpiritual Accompt) <hi>The Virgin, the daughter of</hi> Zion <hi>hath deſpiſed them, and laughed them to ſcorn, the daughter of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>hath ſhaken her head at them,</hi> (2 Kings 19.21.) in the ſtrength of the Lord, as they are his Enemies, becauſe he that ſits in heaven laughs: but they are not to be deſpiſed upon a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Accompt: for</p>
            <p>Firſt, leſs Armies with leſs Advantages, have done a far greater work. The late King of <hi>Sweden</hi> croſs'd the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea with (not above) Eighth thouſand men, and harraſed (almoſt) all <hi>Germany,</hi> ſpoiled their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110136:15"/>Cities, laid their Towns waſte, and ſowed their Field: with deſolation.</p>
            <p>Again, greater Armies (then ours) have miſcarried upon the contempt of weaker Enemies. When the French (under the the Duke of <hi>Alenſon</hi>) had entred <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and poſſeſſed themſelves of the gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they (contemning the weak remaining part of the Enemy) fell to plundering the City, but <hi>they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the experience at a dear rate,</hi> (for they were moſt of them ſlain, the reſt ſhamefully beaten out of the City again by a few that remained unconquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at their entrance.<note n="a" place="margin">Iſte contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptus hoſtium Gallos perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Strad. Bel: Belg.</note> 
               <hi>That a weak Enemy is not to be contemned,</hi> the Spirit of God, and the Experience of all Ages aſſert this, <hi>Though you had ſmitten the whole Army of the</hi> Chaldeans <hi>that fight againſt you, and there remained but wounded men among them, yet ſhould they riſe up every man in his tent, and burn this City with fire,</hi> Jerem. 37.10. <hi>Nihil in hoſtibus vel ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mivictis tuto deſpicitur,</hi> and the Commanders of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have in all Ages found a certain truth in that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Maxim,<note n="b" place="margin">Majorem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perti hoſtem. qui contempſerint ut minorem. Strada Bel: Belgic.</note> 
               <hi>He findes his Enemy ſtrong at a dear rate, who contemns him as weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The deſperate condition of the Enemy may render him not deſpicable.<note n="c" place="margin">Graviſſimi funt morſus irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatae neceſſitatis. Mont.</note> 
               <hi>Neceſsity hath ſharp teeth.</hi> The Commander in chief of the Enemies Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, is (credibly) reported to have brought in a <hi>Crown and Coffin with him.</hi> A Crown is a fair prize, a man will put out the utmoſt of his ſtrength to attain it, the ſhinings of it take a carnal eye ſo far,<note place="margin">A morte propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua vim capiunt Strad. prolus. Statii Stylo.</note> that he will wade to the chin in blood, rather then ſet down any where ſhort of it, and he that muſt die, will ſell his life at as dear a rate as he can:<note n="d" place="margin">Morientium morſus animan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium laetales ſunt Idem Bel: Belg.</note> 
               <hi>Dying creatures bite deadly,</hi> ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110136:15"/>that if the Lord come not upon their ſpirits in his ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, the Victory is like to coſt us dear.</p>
            <p>What the effect of truſting in man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſider.</hi> 3.</note> in your own ſtrength, will be. <hi>Becauſe thou didſt truſt in thy way, in the multitude of thy mighty men, therefore ſhall a tumult ariſe among thy people, and all thy Fortreſſes ſhall be ſpoiled, as</hi> Shalmon <hi>ſpoiled</hi> Betharbel <hi>in the day of battel: the Mother was daſhed in pieces upon her children,</hi> Hoſ. 10.13, 14. God may ſay (if you lean upon the arm of fleſh) They hoped in their Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let it ſave them; They truſted in their Army, let them deliver them; There is a Curſe denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and it will cleave to the man that leaneth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fleſh. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm,</hi> and <hi>whoſe heart departeth from the Lord,</hi> Jerem. 17, 5. If you conſider theſe things aright, you will ſay (with <hi>David</hi> Pſalm 44.6.) <hi>I will not truſt in my bowe, neither ſhall my ſword ſave me.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>When I am weak, then am I ſtrong:</hi> 'Tis a Paradox to carnal Reaſon, but to a ſanctified underſtanding a fair Truth built upon a ſolid rock: We need not fear our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at any time, but we may well be afraid of our ſtrength; we are never ſtronger then when we are weak in our own eyes, never weaker then when we eſteem our ſelves ſtrong in ourſelves: Ceaſe therefore from man, and be intreated once more not to give occaſion to have it ſpoken of our Army what was ſaid of <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Sane Julium Caeſarem non Pompeiani, ſed amici pereme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Sen: de Ira l. 3. c. 20.</note> That <hi>he received not his wounds from the ſwords of Enemies, but from the hands of friends;</hi> If they ſhall return wounded from the hattel, let them not have ground to ſay, (becauſe of your Confidence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110136:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>in them) <hi>Theſe are the wounds with which we were wounded in the houſe of our friends,</hi> Zech. 13.6.</p>
            <p>To conclude, That we may indeed ceaſe from man, and caſt our ſelves and the concernments of our wholly upon God,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 2.5.</note> be exhorted ſecondly to <hi>walk in the light of the Lord,</hi> in the light of his Providence; eye God in the way that he led us hitherro. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Newbery,</hi> and <hi>Marſton,</hi> &amp; <hi>Naſeby;</hi> remember <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar</hi> and <hi>Fife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Videnti Deum omnis creatum eſt auguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>Sterling:</hi> Nothing takes a mans heart off from the creature ſo much as eying God doth. He that walks in the light of Gods providence, findes his heart lifted up to God, the hands of his Confidence ſtrengthned in God. <hi>The Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me out of the paw of the Lion, and out of the paw of the Bear, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philiſtim,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.37. The Lord hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed us a precious firſt-fruit of his Love and Power,<note place="margin">The Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
               </note> he hath given us one token more that he hath not withdrawn himſelf from us, an earneſt of his preſence in the Defeat given to a part of that Army, and ſince the Lord hath evidenced his preſence with us, we may much better ſay of it then <hi>Auguſtus</hi> could of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Nihil ſe non ſperare Tiberio comite, nihil non timere illo deficiente. Suet: in vita Tiber.</note> 
               <hi>That he expected ſucceſs in every underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that</hi> Tiberius <hi>was engaged in, and feared the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of every Deſign in which</hi> Tiberius <hi>had not an hand.</hi> The <hi>Lord of hoſts is with us, the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>is our Refuge.</hi> Remember through what ſtreights he hath brought us, and be confident in the light of his Providence. We may ſay of many acts of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (as he upon the extraction of <hi>Moſes</hi> out of the Waters)<note n="g" place="margin">Quis vel ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum deſponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret in ultimo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſcrimme, cum talia tam mirifice effecta eſſe perſpexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? Prid: ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractionem Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</note> 
               <hi>Who that hath ſeen God leading his people in ſuch a path, opening ſuch or ſuch a door to them, level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110136:16"/>ſuch Mountains before them, and making their way plain, would ever ſuffer his Soul to be caſt down, or his Spirit diſquieted in him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. ult.</note> 
               <hi>None of them that truſt in the Lord ſhall be deſolate.</hi> Be not afraid of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies power: all the ſtrength that is not of God, ſhall be deſtroyed. <hi>Take away her Battlements, for they are not the Lords,</hi> Jerem. 5.10.</p>
            <p>Know the power of the Lord: <hi>If he look upon the earth it trembles, if he touch the mountains they ſmoke, by the blaſt of God his Enemies periſh, by the breath of his noſtrils they are conſumed.</hi> The Lord cannot want help to perform his Councel, to accompliſh his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſince <hi>the Chariots of God are Twenty thouſand, even Thouſands of Angels,</hi> Pſal. 68.17. Study then the name of God, and you will effectually ceaſe from Man. <hi>They that know thy Name, will put their truſt in thee,</hi> Pſalm 9.10.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
